okay uh shall we start so today the um
we actually don't cover General
announcement and then we'll move to the
uh technical discussion directly so
today the the third part of the HD Mar
model is actually the end of the HD
marov model part
so last part so be
patient so today uh the mostly uh the
discussion is actually shallow the first
I will explain about the GMM extension
but the the way we will extend the GMM
is actually quite the straight forward
so I mostly kind of the um explain the
overview uh of how we do that and
actually the all of the kind of
formulation and algorithm almost same
and I will explain about how it is
different
and the another kind of important Al
algorithm is algorithm so that I will
also spend the time and explain it and
hopefully I can finish it bit earlier
and then spend some time for the uh
coding assignment the EXP uh the
explanation uh which is the uh most one
of the most important part of the this
lecture actually so uh coding assignment
is about the
hmm okay so uh let's start uh the to
discuss about the uh the hmm so we are
still stuck in the acoustic modeling
part uh uh since it is based on HD marov
model and then today's uh the discussion
uh before I will move to the gaussian
mixture model I explained that all every
time uh we are working on a single Gaia
model but I already mentioned in the
beginning that the single Gaia model is
not very powerful uh in terms of the
modeling so the uh the today I will
explain about the the extension to the
gaan mixture
model uh it is more powerful but
actually compared with neur netwk is not
so
powerful okay so the the procedure is
actually same as what the I have
explained to the
uh uh you guys about the single question
based approaches uh we use a
introduction of the rate variable
complete data likelihood aary function
and the parameter estimation and I will
explain it one by one but again mostly I
explained that so I
just the remark which part we should
kind of the extend and I didn't kind of
explain about the details uh that in
today's lecture
so first uh we already uh discussed that
the the introduction rat variable in the
hidden Mar model we consider alignment
variable as latent variable but in the
gaan mixture model we actually have to
consider one more uh the extra the lat
variable which I will explain it in the
following
slid so first uh the I already mentioned
that single G
especially with the diagonal calian is
not enough to the capture the complex
pattern in speech uh the the uh the
features and then uh the to efficiently
uh model these kind of patterns actually
we often use the multiple gaan and then
I again we call it the gaan mixture
model and the gaan mixture model is uh
reiten as this kind of a
form there a point yeah so without this
uh the
summation this is actually the Gan
mixture uh single G model there's
nothing kind of special and then the
extension is just the adding the prepare
the gaan distribution uh for the K
components and then just taking the
weighted
sum these are weighted sum so it's
actually similar to the state transition
or the initial transition part uh we
actually uh the have to satisfy the sum
to one condition uh so that it's the
showing the kind of mixture right the
information but basically the equation
extension of the equation is uh like
this and then uh
let's discuss about the uh the latent
variable in the gaan mixture
case so actually similar to the uh
hidden Mark of model cases in the gaan
mixture cases we actually don't know
which
observation are the corresponding to the
this kind of our the each of the
gaussian
so we actually consider all possible uh
the the patterns of the uh the point
that would be represented as a mulle the
gaussian so this is actually almost same
as the the alignment problem right
alignment problem it's uh sorry it's a
one dimension case is but alignment
problem we also try to kind of the
providing one of the data point to be
aligned to uh the each of the uh the
sequence
right and the gusan mixture model is
also using the same alignment variables
which becomes a latent variable and then
uh this is similar to the the alignment
variable is represented by this kind of
the the sequence so this sequence is
actually including all the kind of the
speech feature from one to
T and then this one maybe uh uh belongs
to K 1 maybe belongs to k 2 K = 3 k 4 we
are not
sure so this other the representation is
actually showing that each of the kind
of the cases each of the point whether
this the point is assigned to the one of
the mixture so again this is very
similar to alignment variable that we
introduced before but actually gaan
mixture cases I say it is one of the
kind of typic uh the special case of the
alignment cases where we don't have a
constraint like left to right or three
state or something like that it can be
actually moving to anything so these are
kind of a gaan mixtures are the latent
variable so besides that it is actually
exactly
similar to the uh the alignment variable
uh we are used for the hmm so we
actually are introducing the additional
latent variable b t or the set sequence
of this will be represented as the
uppercase B and this is actually same
lengths as the
observations so these kind of the latent
variables are very similar
to
the uh hmm relat variable and actually
the the mathematical treatment of how to
deal with them is also almost same so
that's why the this lecture I didn't
kind of really redo all the kind of
derivation but I guess you guys could
kind
of understand how we kind of generalize
this uh with the hmm
State okay so now the
we kind of introduce the gaan mixture
the component and then uh this uh the
the uh the the likelihood uh is actually
usually written like this where the uh
gaussian mixture index is also depending
on the
HML so to specify our
problem we actually have our kind of two
are the hidden State one is hmm and the
other is Gan mixture model and then the
other the this means that we also have a
two uh index uh in the the gausia
mixture models so just you know that you
could see that you know each of the hmm
State we will
have uh the mixture index these are
actually the uh the X tension that we
have
performed by the way uh some people may
feel that
the this means that each state would
have a same number of K
right but the it can be actually
changing right some of the state may
have a more gaan gaussian component and
some of the state or some of the even
for may have a smaller uh the the gussan
uh number of gaussian uh the mixtures so
uh this is actually one of the way just
uniformly setting the number of gaussian
component per each state to be the same
but the other kind of extension or our
actual kind of the Practical problem
this part actually can be changed
depending on the the state or upon you
and actually the many of the system are
having such kind of structure and so on
but just for this kind of a lecture as a
Simplicity I will kind of using the the
always using k for this other hmm other
state and so on so and how to set the K
is also a very important the part but
the basically we just empirically
setting this number like a 32 or 64 or
something like that of course we have a
more data we may increase number of
components uh but it's quite empirically
uh
decided and uh there's lot of ways to by
the way are the estimating the number of
the uh the component or even the hmm
State as I mentioned it is always kind
of not three state it can be four or
five uh it can be actually the ch better
to be changed depending on the ph and so
on right and this is actually one of my
the first research when I started speech
research I actually tackle this problem
how to finding this kind of K for each P
or even how to kind of
decide the the states number of states
uh the the the based on the kind of a
various the information criteria so that
was actually my
first the research topic so just reminds
me that some someone actually asked me
how to set a number and so on and just
remind me that my old the work but it it
was not it doesn't become become our the
main stream and the people just using
the empirically setting the total number
1,000 or something like
that okay uh next uh the the once we uh
the the uh introduce the latent variable
which is the one for the the hmm State
and the other for the gausa mixture
component and these are actually again
mathematically very
similar uh
the very similar latent variable so
actually the we can write the complete
data likelihood by simply uh the the uh
introducing the a mixture weight here
like this by the way this derivation is
similar to what we have done in the the
complete data likelihood cases uh by
using the product rule uh the condition
Independence assumption Su Rule and
finally the introducing the concrete
distribution to the kind each of the uh
the equation each of the probabilistic
distribution function but again I didn't
explain this
part because it is quite
straightforwardly
extended oh actually I did prepared it
sorry about that but I I didn't explain
it in the uh the uh this part because it
is just kind of having a additional
latent variable B uh in the the
formulation and so
on and the next part is the the uh the
uh auxiliary function how to make a
auxiliary function and we try to you
know uh the the
the uh making the auxiliary function by
avoiding to uh the use the summation
over the other the state and the in our
cases actually additional the summation
over the sequence is introd used which
is the uh the latent variable for the
GAA mixture
component and the compared with the
previous single gaan cases we actually
have first you know the additional four
terms previously three time this is a
state transition sorry the initial state
state transition and gaan but now we
have a initial state state transition
mixture weight that is additionally
introduced and then uh the gaussian
distribution and the another important
part is that summation is not only with
the the the over the state sequence but
also the Gan mixture component sequence
so this is little bit complicated but
basically the uh now we have a the tools
to uh handle these kind of ways based on
the other the MTH so I basically don't
really kind of explain about it but the
similar to the last lectures by using
the sequence DEC composition uh
distributed property Su Rule and then we
can actually derive the uh
the uh the auxiliary
function and I also want to remark the
two part uh one the the one part of the
remark is that again similar to the uh
previous example summation over the
sequence of S and B are actually the
changed to the summation from J to one
uh J 1 to K and the K called one to
K I think this could into the summation
T I will check it
later think this could should include
summation
T
otherwise right side is depending on the
T okay I will modify it I think this one
should include a summation T but anyway
the uh the another part of the uh the
change is a posterior
distribution in the previous uh
explanation I uh introduced two
posterior distribution in this stage
like one is to uh include the uh the uh
the uh
transition uh the posterior and the
other is the the occupation part and the
occupation part is the probability of we
are some point in the hmm Tois right and
then similarly we also have a kind of a
additional index for the gaussian K this
means that the we are some place in the
Tois and some of the component in the
gaussian and then this is the posterior
probability of representing such kind of
occupation the situation so uh such kind
of the extension happens but generally
this uh the uh the uh the extension
would be done simply by extending the uh
the the previous
methodology so the uh final auxiliary
function is actually written by this
kind of a form where the summation the
the of the sequence is uh converted to
the summation over the hmm State and the
summation over the Gan mixture
component so the by doing the similar
kind of extension we can actually build
the auxiliary
function and then
this
value which is actually the the state
transition part is same but the
occupation part having additional
component by introducing gaan mixture
that is also solved by the forward
backward and again I will skip the order
derivation uh but I just kind of showing
the uh the the algorithm about the
forward algorith the forward
computation uh backward
computation and then the forward
backward
algorithm by the way uh the forward
backward the algorithm uh the
computational cost is also not change so
much we just have our kind of
additional uh the the
multiplication came from the gaan
mixture so of course you know this is
linearly increased but not very
large okay so now uh that we have a the
forward backward algorithm and then get
the kind of each of the uh the
uh the
transition and the uh
occupation uh by uh using the uh the uh
forward probability backward
probability uh State
transition uh the mixture weight and the
gaan and the denominator is a
normalization so by doing that we can
actually compute the uh the transition
probability and similarly we can also
compute the uh occupation probability
but I think this one is very intuitive
this part is actually the almost
same as the
previously
obtained uh the the occupation
probability for each
state and we also have a additional
Factor but this is actually the the
likelihood
ratio of the the component K uh the the
uh the divided by entire
component so this is actually the
probability of uh the uh this uh the the
K the mixture component K so the mixture
component K probability times the the
hmm State the occupation prob probility
becomes this kind of probability so it's
very
intuitive and the last part of the
parameter the estimation again I also
skip this part uh because it's just kind
of having uh the the uh gum uh the the
mixture uh weight component so basically
by using the same mass we can actually
estimating this the mixture weight and
the Cor responding all other parameter
which are almost equivalent to the
previous the estimation
process and the same for the bom we uh
there are some kind of the difference
like including the the mixture weight
here and instead of the estimating the
uh the occupation probability for each
state this is becomes the for each state
and for each mixture component but all
other algorithm same so that I kind of
basically skip
this the explanation but with this
actually the single gaussian hmm is
extended to the gaan mixture model okay
good next last algorithm is the B
algorithm so
I repeat it to mention that we actually
don't know the uh the
alignment uh the deterministic alignment
patterns so that we have to consider all
possible uh the the hmm state right so
then they you know we had a lot of uh
the the uh the the uh the equations to
finally handle this kind of the
summation over the all
sequences uh this is uh that again
because we don't we cannot observe the
hmm alignment the the pattern so we have
to kind of infer them and we use a
probabilistic way which means that we
cannot
deterministically uh the uh Define the
alignment however this is true but we
can actually
estimate the most likely uh the state
alignment by using the similar
techniques and we actually have a
luckily have a such kind of algorithm
called the B and the algorithm so that
will be a kind of a last part of this
kind of
lecture so before uh the the moving to
the uh the B algorithm I will explain a
little bit about the
search so uh
the this is actually one of the let's
say the
pattern of the kind of
graph and then uh let's uh think about
the search problem where we try to find
the highest score accumulated the
highest score pattern as a kind of our
goal by the way such generally also
using the minimum loss so it's a little
bit confusing but I'm we are starting
from the maximum likelihood so I change
it to the highest score so please do not
confuse it so and then uh there are
several algorithm we search beam search
and then I will also expand the betab
algorithm based betab res search and the
uh I will explain the each of the method
search method one by
one so first uh the the uh what is the
highest score so again let just arit
taking one uh the path just this one
this r
one and then we go from here to here and
then accumulating all the score in this
case is two two two
three so the total score is actually
nine right and this it's just by it's
not just a number it is actually our
problem is quite other similar just you
know other I use addition but this is
actually can be replaced as the
probability in this case of course it
the the less than one but anyway that
can be the approximated as the
multiplication of the
probability which we actually introduc
in the many of the cases like you know
the chain rule is multiplication of the
the probability right so actually
getting the kind of a sequence of the
probability corresponding to the getting
the kind of a pass of this one and the
final kind of a the accumulated score
corresponding to the the multiplication
of the product probability in the log
domain by the way log domain okay yeah
so this is actually quite uh the the uh
uh the the uh General uh problem and
actually again the used to uh the uh
represent our
problem okay so this is nine and the
first the search
algorithm uh is gy
algorithm this is actually every time
get the kind of a highest
pass that's starting from here and and
then uh the this one is one and this one
is
two so you're just taking this
one and then next are the two and three
right and then we just the take the
highest one again and now we don't have
any other kind of score uh any other
kind of hypothesis so we just kind of
accumulating this two and three so this
is the greedy algorithm
every time we make a decision just kind
of you know taking the uh the the
highest one in that kind of position
that's it and
fortunately this one two three 2 three
actually better than uh the previous uh
the the pass so this the greedy pass is
actually the one of the way uh to find
the the good uh the the the uh the uh
the score but it is actually as some of
you may you know the note this is
actually a very big
approximation uh and then we will move
to the sh quiz so actually uh the the
the I will show you the answer uh the uh
with the second cases second case beam
search
uh GRE is that we always uh take the
kind of a
top uh the the uh the
result but the this means that you know
for example from here to here this one
might be might get a higher score later
in the accumulation of the kind of
passes right so we are not sure this
kind of a decision is correct or not
and then how to extend this we just
leave uh two kind of
hypothesis four like for example in that
in this case that's always kind of
keeping the two best score so in the
initial part even this one is actually
higher part we just keep this
one uh we just keep the this one as well
so again we are not sure this one can be
better and so on and then let's move to
the next one and from here we actually
have a accumulation of the you know the
plus three and the plus two and here we
also have accumulation plus five and
plus
two and then we actually have a four
possibility and then Computing all kind
of four possibility and then we just
keeping the top
two and interestingly it turns out
actually that actually that this
path still exist or actually this path
is already in this timing higher score
than the GRE search one garch we just go
through here right so the answer is that
already the beam search is almost always
better than greedy
search and then uh doing a similar kind
of the uh the procedure
again and then uh we finally kind of
getting the two
passes and among kind of two passes that
reaching the kind of uh the final goal
and then keeping the highest one and I
explain this with
always the two
hypothesis but of course we can make it
larger it can be you know five or 10 or
thousand and then actually this is the
more are this would be the theoretically
definitely
better but of course this is the also
the increase the cost of the computation
and memory right so the the the also the
k equal one always goes to the the gy
search so uh this is actually the one of
the the beams the one of the search
technique called The Beam search by the
way by doing that it's actually scored
11 and the previously grey s is
10 so actually it turns out that beam
SAR is the getting the better
performance so greedy SAR is not getting
the highest score
unfortunately but uh this is still
approximation right if Kake or very
large it can be more accurate but it is
still up
approximation and the next one is the
bab and the bab is actually not based on
the
approximation we could get the
highest pass by using the special
algorithm so p is actually starting from
the the uh the uh either or of the the
state the posterior or the joint the the
distribution either is fine and in our
the formulation we actually using this
kind of joint distribution of the
observation and the state complete data
like and then the BET algorithm is
actually to uh try to focus on this
value this is that from one to T minus
one to have a maximum
path and then the the score uh that the
given the we are in the St equal J so I
will explain a bit more
detail so again the St equal J means
that we are
some the uh the point in this TR right
for example the case of the the the time
index equal four and the HMF state is
three
then we are
here and then the the
beta the the algorithm is uh the uh
defining this function until here uh
until we reach here uh we try to kind of
get the maximum passes in this cases it
can be this one or it can be the any of
the P but the maximum one it's we if we
found that this is the max maximum one
uh this would become the the BET pass a
bet function given the maximum pass from
here to here and then we get to this
kind of
Point by the way maximum the path from
one to
three can be changed depending on the
position for example again in this cases
the maximum position a ma maximum
position path can be this
one
but in this cases like for example that
the the HM say two cases second Cas
is previous pass cannot be the maximum
pass because it's actually I cannot
reach to this one right we cannot go
from three to two so I just want to
mention that the uh the maximum
pass would depend on where we are
so this function is actually depending
on the the position each of the position
uh we will have a different actually the
max S1 S2 one to T minus we could
get okay so uh this is a kind of
definition but actually this one is the
key function to find the most likely
path so let's formulate it with a
recursive uh way I think it is similar
to what we have done in the uh the
forward and the backward
algorithm so first the the case of tal
one and the uh the the substituting it
to this kind of the the function it is
just uh there's no kind of uh the the uh
the the prior State sequence so this is
actually just a kind of likelihood at
the time stamp
one and then uh let's the work on the
recursive the equation we focus on this
kind of the equation and uh this the
procedure is same as the the the forward
algorithm so I will basically kind of
skip the detail but we use the SE
decomposition a product rule a
conditional Independence assumption and
the Su rule to finally obtain this kind
of the uh the the eive
equation and then we take the Max from
S1 to the one to T minus one but it
stands out that this other Max is
actually represented by the previous uh
the this uh Delta
function so the this is the final
equation uh this uh the Delta equation
is actually de cursively
updated by uh uh the taking the marks
for every kind of the state for all kind
of the time and so on so this is the
another ways to avoid the the the uh the
the old over the possible State speaking
so actually I didn't mention F but this
Max S1 T minus one is very
difficult because this is the
subsequence anyway sequence so we have
to consider all possible sequence so
this is almost
impossible and then the definition of
the function is actually including this
kind of operation which is almost
impossible to solve but it turns out the
decursive equation is actually just
taking the Marx for each
state we avoid to have the maximum of
the the all possible state
subsequence so it is actually very
similar to the forward equation right uh
the forward equation also the avoid all
possible St SE summation by using the
for recursive equation and betab
algorithm is also similarly actually the
the they making it like
this and the after the uh the we perform
this kind of a the
sequence sorry the incremental operation
from one to T and then let's think about
the last part so last part uh if we kind
of in uh the the uh the substituting
this small T to large T which is the the
end of our kind of sequence and then uh
after this recursive uh the the
maximization step which doesn't hover uh
the the the consider the all possible
State
sequence uh it actually turns out that
this uh the operation is corresponding
to what we wanted to solve in the
beginning
which is this operation so after this
the the other kind of the processing is
finished in the last the time frame this
actually uh the uh the corresponding to
solve this other
equation and the yes we have some
approximation comes from the
hmm But at given the HM mm we actually
don't use any kind of a approximation
like a beam search and so on we actually
consider all possible State sequence uh
given the kind of hmm assumption and
then this uh the the algorithm is
actually the the the derived so by doing
this one we can actually find the most
likely uh State sequence uh without the
any
approximation and then the move to the
next
Quiz so the answer is the BW the
algorithm yeah so especially in the case
of the the the graph uh the the as you
see that you know beam search uh the gy
search is the worst and the beam search
is actually the better but as I
mentioned the BET algorithm providing
the best most likely uh pass so I will
actually show you that so I thought it's
maybe good to do that in the the
homework but anyway I will explain it so
uh the first this is a very simple
version of the
bet the the recursive function where I
only kind of include the state
transition but uh the uh the in the real
situation we we actually also have a
gausian mixture part so there are some
difference right but it's just you know
the thinking always you know gaan part
is kind of a say providing the same
score and so on and then again the uh
the BET algorithm is the AL is a way to
find the best uh the the the state
sequence and then I computed each kind
of uh the beta the function one by one
from you know the the t two cases here
and here we compute the um beta function
score and then moving to the next the
frame and comput the kind of all cases
and moving the next case and Computing
everyone all the kind of cases and then
finally uh reaching the uh the
end of the uh the
sequence and then actually uh taking the
best score uh the the passes uh which is
the Cod back track the technique that is
also included in the algorithm part of
my lecture but anyway the answer is
actually this
one and let's check it actually this
betab score is 15
uh way better than
the uh greedy score or beam such
score so betore actually can find the
most likely the
sequence by the way why you know this
kind of a thing happen is that there's
the very large the score
here come up with this graph is not easy
you know come up with the graph that you
know the greedy is worse
than beam such and beam such is worse
than the yeah I found this kind of you
know very typical example but generally
if we don't care you know beam such is
actually not bad and then beam such and
the beta would be a same score and so on
so it took time to actually come up with
this the score in the
graph and the uh this is the beta I just
kind of summarize the our recursive part
how to compute and then also finally to
get to this kind of uh the the the uh
the path we actually need to kind of
save the pointer so I actually also
including this the
pointer part in the the BET
algorithm okay this is is the about the
B algorithm and then I will quickly go
through the actually the
training so uh we actually explained
about for backward algorithm for the
backward computation to consider the all
possible summations but actually this
part is depl to the BET algorithm bet
pass so for backward consider all kind
of passes and the BET pass cases we only
consider the one pass that is obtained
the by the the betab algorithm and then
algorithm is actually become
simpler previously we have to consider
the all possible kind of even after the
kind of uh the the uh the the
the auxilary function and so on and
avoid to have our summation over the SE
we still have to consider the sum or the
the the state and so on state index and
so on but by using the bet the
approximation we just consider this part
so we don't have to consider this part
of the summation and the so one so it's
actually the saving the the
computational cost and this uh is
practically not a very bad
approximation uh many of the system are
actually also using this other the B uh
training and so on by the way why this
is not so bad
it's empirically we knew that this betab
pass is very peaky the very high
probability compared with all other
passes so bet pass is almost for example
90% And then rest of the kind of passes
are the very small probability uh so due
to that actually betaing is quite
popular by the way this doesn't mean
that the hard backward is the useless
for backward is very important in the
case first for example forward is a way
to also compute the lik right and hard
backward is also sometimes very
important when uh the the the
distribution does not become peaky which
also happens in the case that for
example the speech is very noisy and so
on in this case we are not sure which
one is a very correct alignment and the
probability does not become peaky and
the many probability becomes actually a
similar probability in this case for
backward is still important and so on
but as a kind of a simple training Al
algorithm the B training is quite often
used where the the instead of using the
the forward backward algorithm we just
using a b algorithm and then Computing
the sufficient statistics and then
updating the parameter and so on so this
is actually the simpler version of the
backward and this is actually main part
of the uh the the homework of this uh
the the coding assignment so let's
summarize this talk and move to the
explanation about it so first hmm GMM
extension is quite kind of
straightforward we just introducing the
latent variable and then GMM extension
is performed and we also explain out the
V betab is the most likely sequence no
approximation without be we can get the
best
SE and this bet search is actually used
to also that simplify the training and
so on